Guide to the Herbert F. Janick Jr. Papers MS 012
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
- Series 3: Subject Files, 38885
  - Oral Histories - Student Work - Introduction to Historical Research, 38894
    - Western Connecticut State University -- History., 38895
      - Stacy Wahl (interview) Creator: Wahl, Stacy Interviewer(s): Joe Oppedisano and Anabela Marques Interview location: Wahl's home in Ridgefield, CT Running time: 75 min., Apr 23, 1991; 38905; Number of tapes:2 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 12, Item 76, 77)
        Topics discussed: (tape 1;side A): Starting at Western; was helping the students in her son's class w/ their reading skills; was asked by Dr. Braun if she would do the same the teacher at Western; Orthotectracidecahedran model; was asked by the head of biology department if she could make one; didn't know what it was until her son showed her a picture of it; used a piece of cheese as her rough draft; traced it and ended up w/ five different models; had her students make these models using cardboard, wood, and plastic; Math classes; aspects of how to teach Intro to Calculus; Models; developed several models to help students better understand math; suggested all students use them before taking a test; Controversy over the "toys"; was told she was a concept teacher, not a math educator; she wouldn't use the word "methods" in her teaching to avoid it; Changes at WestConn; friendly w/ Dr. Haas as a motherly figure; atmosphere isn't the warm and friendly one it once was; size has had a role in this; teacher training was the role school had but now it is almost a bad to say that phrase; Former students; Rewards of teaching; go beyond a paycheck; Training teachers; didn't supervise in the classroom; felt students should pass an arithmetic test (later state implemented it); Her book; got idea from a student while teaching in Colorado; "Counting Petals" was the name of it; came out in 1976 in paperback; many bookstores didn't carry it because it was published by non; profit group and bookstores couldn't charge 40% profit; her book won an award; book was meant to help in teaching children math; Her husband, John; he was a PhD physicist; met him in Iowa; married and had children; while he was working at getting his PhD, she taught at University of Iowa; Teaching was her passion; Patens; both her and husband had patens on their projects; Quality of teaching at WestConn; quality depends on the individual; teachers at WestConn care about students; Students evaluation; Dr. Janick came out on top of the student evaluation; most evaluation ranked non; PhD teachers higher (tape 1;side B): Background; her and husband taught first wave of returning GIs; goal was to get a generation of math lovers and not haters; Recognition for her models; went to Georgia to display her models; has gone various places to talk about her models; Full professorship; was first woman to receive full; professorship w/out terminal degree (PhD); Science institute; in 1963, got to teach at a Nation Science Institute; Teaching methods; would have students look for a pattern in order to better understand math; felt making a game out of math made learning much more easier; brought her own grandchildren in once to a classroom and had them make models using marshmallows and toothpicks; WestConn memories; liked her time there; was angry they never had a couch for female faculty to rest in lounge; Quonset Hut; Elementary school teachers and foreign language; had a meeting where discussed whether elementary teachers should know a foreign language (she felt it was necessary); Dr. Rosenberg; he was a history teacher before she came; both went to Columbia University; he taught her niece Algebra; wrote about history of WestConn; Competition w/ her siblings; she was youngest of ten children; tried to match what they all did, including getting a paten; Course to get a patent; her and husband went to see a lawyer about getting a patent for one of her models; she kept getting turned down for a patent in the beginning; encouraged to appeal and turn to educators for help; told someone else had the patent, but when she contacted one of these two, he said it was different; Students; get her creativity results in the classroom; Textbooks; doesn't like ordering textbooks, but she is required to do so; Basic Studies students in beginning couldn't afford to textbook; Life before teaching; she was a dishwasher before she got into teaching; her husband was a plumber's helper (tape 2;side A): Class size; her concepts class had about 48 students; "Dot Movie"; spent about eleven hours making a four minute movie; she used it for demonstration for both math and music majors; Basic Studies class; once had a class where most class were football players; the class was so bad it almost made her quit because of their attitude; Her Family; husband was a brilliant man; one son was a math scholar, other was a finalist; daughter is a computer programmer who went into Peace Corps and learn several foreign languages; accomplishments of her children; her mother only got to the 6th grade, but had a lot of creativity; Writing her memoirs; going to write and publish herself; wanted to write a record of the family for her grandchildren; stories about her family and memorable stories
      - Dr. Truman Warner (interview) Creator: Warner, Dr. Truman Interviewer(s): (no name given) Interview location: Midtown campus Running time: 90 min., May 1, 1996; 38904; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 12, Item 80)
        Coverage: 1930s-1996
        Topics discussed: (side A): Changes to the university; went from a 2 year to 3 year then to a 4 year school; name change from Danbury State Teacher's College to Danbury State College to Western CT State College then University; addition of liberal arts; WW II and enrollment; GI Bill lead to increase; allowed him to get his graduate degrees; was in 88th division in war and went from North Africa to Italy then France; Labor unions at WestConn; AAUP (then AFG, a smaller group); times which faculty and administration worked together w unions to get more funds and raise salaries; Students sometimes got involved; never any strikes, just threats; CSU system; should be independence from the board; feels Western is always last and Central's connection gets things passed; feels each university should have own identity; Governors and politicians relationships w/ WestConn; Clark Hull, Bill Ratchford, and other local politicians been very helpful; Governor Dempsey was also helpful; not sure were Governor Rowland stands; Teaching style; doesn't feel he has changed, just added/altered according to class size; "Do; Day" and Interim Program; Politically informed students; more so in past than today (side B): WestConn as student and faculty; began as a student in 1937; began as Director of Admissions in 1958; taught anthropology and history; Western changes; great extent is because of numbers; he knew everyone in the classes between 1940; 1942, not case today; building structures; impact on way of teaching (both positive and negative); Political events of country and effect on WestConn; talked to several students about their concerns about fighting/being drafted into the Vietnam War; "teach ins" during the Vietnam War; His collection of articles and other things; Race relations on campus; number of black students was small; Changes in student expectations; initially everybody who came here did so to become teachers; Dr. Haas; not sure if she encountered sexism; began as Dean of Women; always here early and always available; Knew all the principles/presidents of school; Dr. Higgins lived in his neighborhood as he was growing up
      - Dr. Truman Warner (interview) Creator: Warner, Dr. Truman Interviewer(s): Joe Bukowski and Cindy Beck Interview location: White Hall basement Running time: 65 min., Apr 25, 1991; 38903; Number of tapes:2 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 12, Item 78, 79)
        Topics discussed: (tape 1;side A): Changes in students; as a student, it was a teacher's college; there was a certain appearance you needed to have (ties, suits, etc.); expectations of teachers had to be met; graduating class was small; Old Main; everything was in there (classrooms, gyms, library, etc.); White Hall; was Danbury High School; Fairfield Hall; only dorm; Had excellent teaching opportunities at DSTC; Many teachers had come from the New School; it was part of Columbia University; DSTC size; faculty knew everybody; better ratio of students to teachers than now; Influx of men; brought in several different backgrounds (like sciences); students were all exposed to different types of classes; Arts; Atmosphere; small college brought more unity; Time in army; had letters censored if an enlisted man; people would comment on his letters and the detail he used; credits this to exposure he had at DSTC to variety of courses; Expectations; expected teachers should have some knowledge of variety of things; didn't have status Yale did, but gave exposure to students nonetheless; Lab Schools; used Balmforth, Locust, and other schools; Roberts Ave wasn't around at the time he was a student; Education process; began freshman year w/ observation and by senior year, students had been exposed to the teaching field; Other State Teacher's Colleges; all but Western have moved from their original location; Time at DSTC; started in 1937 and graduated in 1941; came back in 1958 as director of admissions; Background; had his Master's from Columbia (later Ph. D from same place); had been teaching high school Briarcliff Manor, NY; Director of Admissions; DSTC needed some to take care of admissions and recruitment; before entrance, all students had to be interviewed; he had to make the arrangements for this; Interview process; asked about their high school, etc.; meant to see what type of student they were; Interim Program; expected by all students to do some work outside during intersession; faculty would visit them to see what they were doing; worked into students schedules; provided many opportunities for the students; DSTC as a progressive school; ideas of John Dewey; more hands; on activities; Botany and use of Squantz Pond as a lab a project of the CCC (New Deal organization); went on field trips; Geology department; the demise of the department; believes it was based on matters other than motivations; perhaps antipathy towards Dr. Groff leads to it as well as politics; State's role; cost for students was minimal ($15 per semester when he went); it was an opportunity for an education the state provided students; Choice of college; couldn't afford to go to Yale; told about possible scholarship late (hadn't taken college boards yet); Higher education; things have changed; greater need for money; war came and influenced things; additional buildings; Dr. Lathrop Higgins; former head of school; Higgins Hall named for him; extremely interested in science; Inflation; CT reputation on higher education; is poor, ranks in bottom of the 50 states; outside Normal Schools, CT never gave much to higher education; Expectation of professors and teachers; getting published; getting a job out of school; Howard Durgy; was here for years; longest employed person in state for a long time (tape 1;side B): Student attitudes; students in school to basically get a job; most aren't here to get an education; past education of students plays role in how they view higher education; Special programs; developed to attract more students; Basic studies; there have been many who have become great students; some have gone on to get Master's and doctorates; hates to generalize type of students; Course development; likes to combine courses; Dedication of students; change in technology, w/ emphasis on learning from television, has had an effected on way students learn; reading something stays w/ you longer than seeing it on television; television has altered generations; many students today don't want to learn; Athletes and students; some students are just coming to college to play sports; Changes in Social Science department; there weren't departments in the beginning of the college; had someone who specialized in these areas to teach classes; the concentrations have become highly specialized; number of students have had an effect on program; Tom West; a judge in Danbury; a student of his wrote a great paper; Change of curriculum; core requirements; number have had effect on requirements to be met by students; Major requirements; determined by committees; believes often come from a priority some people have; Geology department demise; Barbara Obeda carried on geology courses for a while; invited to join social science department, higher up wouldn't allow it; Campus causes; overall students haven't been very active as a group; individually many have been active and vocal; 1960s riots didn't occur at WestConn, but spillover was felt in terms of dress and attitude; Dr. Haas; felt strongly about how people should carry themselves; women shouldn't wear slacks; Streaking; was seen on campus a little bit; Minorities at WestConn; few in numbers; not done on purpose; hard to attract minorities; Music students; Alcohol and drug abuse; not a major problem at WestConn, but it does go on; a major problem through out the country (tape 2;side A): Prejudice on campus; doesn't believe it is a major problem on campus; believes it goes both ways; Gay community; quiet community; only contact w/ them is when a student approaches him w/ problems; Women's groups; Working students; many are working too much for their own benefit; high school students are similar in terms of working too much; Lack of involvement; those who have least involvement are quickest to complain, this includes faculty and students; last SGA election had only 250 people voting; more people need to get involved, vote, etc.
      - Howard Williams (interview) Creator: Williams, Howard Interviewer(s): Rob Cappelli and Mike Hennessy Interview location: White Hall Running time: 65 min., May 3, 1991; 38902; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 12, Item 82)
        Coverage: 1965-1990
        Topics discussed: (side A): Interest in music; both parents were involved in music; his family was heavily music oriented; learned to play the trombone during hard times of the Depression; worked in a church in his youth singing in the choir; Start in music; Mansfield College in Pennsylvania during WW II; got degree in music education; played trombone in Air Force for 4 years; first teaching job was in Wilksburg, Pennsylvania and built music program; Offers to play w/ bands; Ralph Flanagan Band; WestConn; came in 1965 to teach music; taught until 1988; department chair at time was a friend from Mansfield College; Student/faculty changes; it was still primarily a teacher's college when he first came; began a jazz ensemble 5; 6 years after arriving; taught jazz last 10 years at WestConn; Music department; was large by 1970s; bachelor of arts program in music; later bachelor of music added; Business school; many dropped out to join business school in 1970s; many teacher's programs were effected by the addition of business; Standards; higher now than they were then; some students were just average then; interest varies w/ student (more dedicated today); Relationship w/ administration and faculty; Dr. Haas was great for the music program; school was closer in beginning because of size of the college; music department grew over the years (originally located in Berkshire); Business program effect on school; music department felt not enough money going into department; feeling was music was getting left behind; now music and business are more balanced; Music preferences; in classroom, focused on the music there; outside classroom, their favorite style (like rock); Charles Ives; knew little about him before coming to WestConn; Vietnam War; hard for teachers to get students to listen; felt students believed the world owed them; no respect for teachers; many protests back then; Prejudice at WestConn; didn't see any problems; James Furman; shared an office w/ him; Teaching philosophy; changes in type of music; make students more rounded through various types of music; computers changed how music is used and taught; Marching band; school wanted one for the football team; hard to establish because of economic reasons; Mr. Smith got it going eventually; didn't need to be music major to be in marching band; Concerts; Relationship between departments; always some problems; feels slowed down; problems became very serious at one point; Relationship w/ presidents of college; Dr. Haas always supportive and came to all concerts; Dr. Bersi and Dr. Feldman never been close to department; they attended the occasional concert; Dr. Haas; open door policy; great person (side B): Local music programs; Newtown has a great one; others have poor programs; when CT is going well, music is as well; the reverse holds true as well; High school music programs; start preparing students for college; Ways in which people listen to music; Type of student; most came from middle; class backgrounds; usually dedicated and hard working; Relationship w/ students; always great; holds his first class in fond memory because being his first class; class of 1969 also has fond memories for him; Course development; History of Jazz; Music Appreciation; Jazz; evolution of jazz; big band music; origins in rock and other types of music; Advent of the CD; brings new appreciation to jazz; more younger people are listening to jazz today; Retirement; still tries to make concerts and recitals at WestConn; holds emeritus title, so he has full campus privileges
      - Howard Williams (interview) Creator: Williams, Howard Interviewer(s): Jean Bird and Jen Marzucca Interview location: White Hall room #219 Running time: 60 min., Aug 30, 1992; 38901; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 12, Item 83)
        Topics discussed: (side B): Glen Miller Band; thrill of a lifetime and fulfilled a lot of music aspirations for him; got to do a lot of things while being in the band; treated like royalty everywhere they went; Poland; went there while he was in the Glen Miller Band; at the time (1957), everything was in terrible conditions; meet w/ a warm reception at Warsaw; played there for a week and then traveled around Poland for a week; Joining the Glen Miller Band; by time he joined the band, Miller had died (while in WW II); Ray McKinley was his drum and continued Miller's music; Miller had organized it in CT originally; Qualifications for joining a band; depends on what the band is looking for; he played the trombone and were looking for someone who could lead; he had been playing in a local band in Pennsylvania; McKinley liked what he heard and asked him to join; joined the band, took leave of absence from job, and went on tour; Goals; they hard to achieve, but should never been given up on; Music of the Glen Miller Band; used some of the original works of Glen Miller and Ray McKinley; also used new works; "My Prayer"; was a solo done by Miller on original record; he later played same song on later record (both sounded the same); always asked to play the song; Ed Sullivan Show; wild experience because the Clyde Beanie Circus was on same show; smell and noise of animals made things wild; played "Chattanooga Choo Choo"; Background; graduated from Mansfield Teacher's College in 1950 (Mansfield, Pa); went into service after graduation for four years; taught in Wilkesbury schools; got opportunity to Mountain Top (outside Wilkesbury) to start a program from scratch and took it; no program w/ little equipment; didn't have instruments in beginning, so he asked everybody in community to donate any instruments they had; eventually had a band and had hired teachers (did it all in beginning); Beginning at WestConn; a former classmate of his at Mansfield was chair at Western; called him up to ask him if he wanted to come to Western; came up for interview and meet Dr. Haas; Dr. Haas; when he meet her, first question was what he thought of Lawrence Welk; addressed him as "Howie" when she first meet him; got along really well w/ her and enjoyed working w/ her; Changes in music department; small department at first, it increased but decreased again; Jazz ensembles he was in charge of; a lot of Ives Festivals (Fine Arts Festival); by late 1970s, music became less popular and business took charge; teacher salaries later rose to become respectable; stricter qualifications to become a music teacher; Liberals Arts degree; becoming more popular; popular w/ those who wish to have private teaching/tutoring; Cuts to program; budget cuts has an effect on programs; makes things difficult; don't hire someone to replace someone who retires (music supervisors); Student qualifications (to play at Ives Auditorium); the department makes the decision as who gets in; during height in early 1970s, had more than enough students where they were able to hold auditions; way to separate those who can and those who can't; students needs to pass qualification to get into the program; Teacher; student relationship; best feature of the music department; students keep him young; more students, so less opportunity to know all of them; First WestConn class; Experiences w/ students; many pranks and jokes were played by students and faculty; Challenges by the students; during 1960s, some student demonstrations; Basic music courses; course taught to non; music students; one of the students he had never had any exposure to music, so he had to adjust rules for him (had him sang "My Country Tis of Thee" in tune); blind students are easy to work w/ as their hearing is great (most difficult thing is the sheet music) (side A): WXCI; too much of one kind of music; "music snobbery"; there should be more diversification; Types of music; diversification is necessary to have deeper appreciation; Station involvement; used to help w/ the Jazz program on the station in beginning; hasn't been involved in years; Location of the music department; first came, it was located in Berkshire; moved to White Hall in 1968 (only by half); it was Danbury Junior High School in 1968 still and had to share it them; Car on stage; in Berkshire Hall, a door in back; at time, a faculty member owned a small car that ended up on the stage; Harry Connick, Jr.; gaining more respect in the industry; enjoys him; is on top of the world and a great actor; Introduction of the Bachelor of Music degree; wasn't instituted until 1970; reason was because it was primarily a teacher's college in beginning; became more diversified in programs offered at the college; Reflection on time at WestConn enjoyed most aspects of his time at WestConn; enjoyed working in the school; loved the students and faculty members; hated the politics; well respected institution and proud to be associated w/ it
      - Dr. Robert Wolsch (interview) Creator: Wolsch, Dr. Robert Interviewer(s): Marc Garrety and Andy Davidson Interview location: unknown Running time: 85 min., ca.Jun 18, 1905; 38900; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 12, Item 84)